Guide to the Christopher Phillips Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- September 1987 - February 1991, London Again: Producing Books in Bloomsbury, Series XIII
  - Juliet Man Ray [1911-1991]: early attempts by me and by John Calmann's book packaging firm to produce a book based on her life; envelope for oral history microcassette;correspondence mentioning other oral histories she had done; unpublished interview with her by a man in Spain; obituaries, and a short obituary addendum by Lynn MacRitchie published in The Independent newspaper of London; the unpublished first draft of Lynn MacRitchie's ghost-written Afterword to my edition of Self Portrait, which contains more material about Julie than appeared in the published version; photograph of Juliet's chic housekeeper, Geneviève Le Goff; photograph of Juliet, probably in summer 1987, working with Jerry Gold at her apartment on the Rue d'Assas, Paris, 1986-1991 (Box 103, Folder 210)
    - Original oral history mini-cassette [1] that I made with Julie and her brother Joe Browner in Paris, March 10, 1986, 1 (Box 103A)
  - Juliet Man Ray: Sotheby's catalogue of the sale of her collection in London; includes palette-shaped invitation to reception, 1995 March 22-23 (Box 103, Folder 211)
  - Riding the Skies: Classic Posters From the Golden Age of Flying, With an Introduction by Jan Morris [Bloomsbury Publishing, London, £16.95]; designed by Graham Davis Associates, London. Correspondence and contracts, including with Jan Morris, British Airways, Imago print-production consultants, Bloomsbury Publishing; lists of posters as the contents evolved, 1987-1989 (Box 103, Folder 212)
  - Riding the Skies: transparencies and graphics, including a history of the B.O.A.C. Speedbird logo; Polaroid photographs taken by me of vintage posters that were not used in the book, 1987-1989 (Box 103, Folder 213)
  - Riding the Skies: my sales kit, dummy, specification sheet and the pack of B.O.A.C.-poster postcards I used for my sales meeting with publishers; my list of sales points I wrote for use by the Bloomsbury sales force, 1988 (Box 103, Folder 214)
  - Riding the Skies: finding artists of the 1930's, 40's and 50's and their heirs to clear rights and permissions -before the days of the Internet; correspondence with some of the surviving artists, including Abram Games, Theyre Lee-Elliott and Fougasse, 1988 (Box 104, Folder 215)
  - Riding the Skies: a history of the airline industry that I wrote for Jan Morris as background for her Introduction [an elaborate production, with sections keyed to the specific posters in the book], 1988 July (Box 104, Folder 216)
  - Riding the Skies: promotion and reviews; spring 1989 Bloomsbury Publishing catalogue (Box 104, Folder 217)
  - Arabia Deserta, by Charles M. Doughty, with an Introduction by T.E. Lawrence and Foreword by Patricia, Countess Jellicoe [Bloomsbury Publishing, London, £16.95]; designed by David Fordham. Correspondence, production materials, print estimates and my financial calculations; the editorial style book I created for the project. [My sales presentation folder that I used for publishers is with the Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis material; sales dummy layouts by David Fordham are in flat oversize carton No. 109], 1987-88 (Box 104, Folder 218)
  - Arabia Deserta: photographic research and notes for vintage photographs of Arabia and bedouin life. From Gertrude Bell Archive, University of Newcastle-Upon-Tyne; St. Anthony's College, Oxford; Royal Geographical Society, London; and elsewhere, 1988 (Box 105, Folder 219)
  - Arabia Deserta: vintage photographs of Arabia and bedouin life used in the book. By Gertrude Bell, H. St. John Philby, Sir George Rendel, Capt. William Shakespear and others; approximately 114 photographs. These are copy prints made for the project, 1988 (Box 105, Folder 220)
  - Arabia Deserta: vintage photographs of Arabia and bedouin life NOT used in book. Most have still never been published. 154 photographs, plus photocopies of engravings and line drawings from the original 1888 edition of Arabia Deserta; includes some duplicate prints of photographs used in book. All have notes on the back by me keying them to specific chapters. These are copy prints made for the project, 1988 (Box 106, Folder 221-222)
  - Arabia Deserta: original 600,000-word text with first cuts by Lynn MacRitchie marked in it: my working copy, 1988 (Box 106, Folder 223)
  - Arabia Deserta: my complete manuscript, every word typed by me; old-fashioned floppy discs (originals) of manuscript, 1988 (Box 106, Folder 224)
  - Arabia Deserta promotion: the sales kit I wrote, with selling points, for the use of the Bloomsbury Publishing sales force, 1989 (Box 107, Folder 225)
  - Arabia Deserta: promotion, reviews and correspondence about a possible U.S. edition; correspondence about a successful sale of rights for a text-only Italian edition, 1989 (Box 107, Folder 226)
  - In transition: A Paris Anthology, With an Introduction by Noël Riley Fitch [Doubleday, $25, and Anchor paperback, $14.95; Secker & Warburg, London, £17.95]; designed by David Fordham. Correspondence, contracts, estimates and production materials. [Copies of all correspondence with Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis is in with her material. Sales presentation folder I used for publishers is also in with Onassis material. Sales dummy layouts by David Fordham are in Box 108, with film.], 1988-1990 (Box 107, Folder 227-228)
  - Paris Anthology: illustrations, 1989 (Box 107, Folder 229)
  - Paris Anthology: rights and permissions, including the process of tracking down writers of the 1920's or their heirs or agents, before the days of the Internet or e-mail [all Kay Boyle material is in her file], 1989 (Box 107, Folder 230-232)
  - Paris Anthology: reviews, 1990 (Box 107, Folder 233)
  - Paris Anthology: David Fordham's dummy spreads (3); actual film [transparencies] used by Doubleday for printing, 1990 (Box 108, Folder 234-242)
    Transparencies were originally stored in two boxes. There was a note on box 1 (containing pages 1-111) that read: "endpaper film (different front and back) and illustration film are in this box. CP 16/1/90".
  - Sales dummy spreads by the London designer David Fordham for two book projects: Arabia Deserta (6); and Vasari's Lives of the Painters (8). [Vasari jacket is in with the other Vasari material in its "book idea" file], 1988-1989 (Box 109, Folder 243-244)
  - Book ideas: examples of bindings and design ideas I wanted to try, plus work by one amazing National Geographic wildlife photographer, 1987-1990 (Box 110, Folder 245)
  - Book idea: With the Kennedys by Barry Chamish [novella, brought from Israel], 1987 (Box 110, Folder 246)
  - Book idea: Japan Day by Day, by Edward S. Morse: very amusing illustrations for dummy, 1987 (Box 110, Folder 247)
  - Book idea: Hours in the National Gallery, by Stewart Dick [Vol. 1] and John Steegman [Vol. 2]. The idea was to make an illustrated edition of these excellent 1920's books, possibly for National Gallery Publications, London, 1987 (Box 110, Folder 248)
  - Book idea: Stanley: How I Found Livingston. Includes specifications, illustrations and correspondence with Stanley's descendants, whom I visited to gather material, 1987 (Box 110, Folder 249)
  - Book idea: Eyes Right: The Ultimate Celebrity Spotting Book. Dummy for this project, whose idea was to show only the eyes of various celebrities in a guessing game of whom they belonged to, 1988? (Box 110, Folder 250)
  - Book idea: Israeli Women of Achievement by Beverly Mizrachi, an Israeli sociologist and my close friend. Contains envelopes for cassettes; also a booklet by Mizrachi, published in 1989 by the American Jewish Committee, that incorporates some of the interviews and research, 1988-1989 (Box 110, Folder 251-252)
    - important cassettes (16 original) of oral history by Mizrachi with prominent Israeli women
      - Naomi Amir, M.D., 3 (Box 185–187)
      - Amira Dotan, Brigadier-General, Israel Defense Forces, 3 (Box 188–190)
      - Shulamit Lapid, author, 3 (Box 191–193)
      - Rina Mor, Miss Universe, 3 (Box 194–196)
      - Chana Marron, actress, 2 (Box 197–198)
      - Vivian Silver, kibbutz founder, 2 (Box 199–200)
  - Book idea: Vasari's Lives of the Painters: Correspondence, negotiations and pricing estimates; table of contents; dummy jacket by David Fordham [dummy layouts by David Fordham are in flat oversize carton No. 109], 1989 (Box 111, Folder 253)
  - Book idea: Erte and the Folies Bergère: correspondence with Charles Spencer, 1990 (Box 111, Folder 254)
  - Book idea: Inspiration Day by Day, a book of daily readings, 1990 (Box 111, Folder 255)
  - Book idea: Churchill's History of North America, 1990 (Box 111, Folder 256)
  - Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis [1929-94]: correspondence with her as an editor at Doubleday, including personal notes by me and my own impressions of our meetings; also our correspondence about my move back to New York and the letters she wrote for me when I was job-hunting in New York, 1990-91 [copies of all this material are also in their appropriate files], 1988-1991 (Box 111, Folder 257)
  - Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis: my sales kit, which she loved, for Arabia Deserta, the first book I showed her and which she tried to acquire for Doubleday. [The dummy spreads that she also loved, by David Fordham, are in Box 109], 1988 April (Box 111, Folder 258)
  - Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis: my sales kit for In transition: A Paris Anthology, which she loved and did acquire for Doubleday [the dummy spreads that she also loved, by David Fordham, are in Box 60, with the film], 1988 December (Box 111, Folder 259)
  - Kay Boyle [1902-92]: our correspondence, signed book inscription to me, signed photograph to me, 1988-1992 (Box 111, Folder 260)
  - Wilfred Thesiger [later Sir Wilfred, 1910-2003]: my letters to him about Arabia Deserta, which resulted in a meeting. [He gave his blessing to my condensed and edited version of the text and wrote a blurb for the jacket, calling it "the very essence of that perceptive masterpiece"] Also, his photograph in a magazine article about explorers; the title page of his autobiography, signed for me, 1989 (Box 111, Folder 261)
- 1950-2005: About My Life as a Whole and the Making of This Archive, Series XIV
  - My Book of Days to Remember: perpetual calendar date book marked with anniversaries of significant events in my life and other people's [photocopy: I have original book, which I am still adding to], 1950-2005 (Box 112, Folder 1)
  - Five oral history cassettes (original) I made in Jerusalem in 1986. The interviewer is Mordechai Tobin, an older man who moved to Jerusalem in later life to be a Baal Tshuvah [a Newly Orthodox Jew] and to study at Ohr Somayach yeshiva. By the time I made these tapes, I had broken with Orthodox Judaism, but I did not discuss this in my interviews with Mr. Tobin
    - Envelopes (Box 112, Folder 2-3)
    - Recordings, 5 (Box 201–205)
  - Selected relics of collecting, preserving and organizing the material in this archive: includes letters I've written over the decades to gather material and track people down; correspondence from the Collegiate School archivist, who made copies of certain things [See also correspondence with Eton archivist in Series II]; photocopies of envelopes in which I have preserved certain papers; lists of files that I shipped all over the world as I moved; annotated inventories of my boxes placed in document storage after my return to New York; some letters over the years in which I mentioned the collection I was amassing, 1950-2005 (Box 112, Folder 4)
  - The Documenter's Document of Documents. Photocopy of the cover of a 1959 car magazine whose cover tore off through constant use: in 1964 [at age 13], I fixed the cover with Scotch tape and wrote next to it in pencil the date on which I placed the tape there, 1964 March 25 (Box 112, Folder 5)
  - Preliminary memos and descriptions of the collection that formed part of my early discussions with the Yale Library, 2003-2004 (Box 112, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, lists and other relics from the final sorting and filing process as I readied the collection for the Yale University Library; includes material from the October 2004 visit to New York of my brother David F. Phillips, a trained librarian, to help with the project, 2004-2005 July 7 (Box 112, Folder 7)
  - Photographs of the 63 cartons stacked in my bedroom ready for collection, on July 7, 2005, by the Yale Library's movers (Box 112, Folder 8)
  - A list of future projects I'd like to accomplish with this archive: my wish list. If there is demand, I will try to accomplish these projects, either for a specific series or the whole collection, sooner rather than later, 2005 (Box 112, Folder 9)
- Diaries, 1971-1991; Series XV
  Diaries consist of notebooks in a wide assortment of sizes; cassettes; and groupings of loose pages. They are arranged chronologically and each diary has been assigned a number, which is located in the upper right-hand corner of the outside cover. All cassettes in this series should be considered as originals, unless otherwise noted in the inventory.
  - 1-14, 1971 March 13-1974 August 13 (Box 113, Folder 1-5)
  - 15-20, 1975 September 15-1977 February 9 (Box 114, Folder 6-7)
  - 21: Christopher Phillips talking, " Architectural Digest gossip", 1977 December 28; 1 (Box 114A)
  - 22-26, 1978-1979 (Box 114, Folder 8-9)
  - 27, 1979 January 16; 1 (Box 115)
    Recorded in the evening.
  - 28: Christopher Phillips talking into tape recorder on trip to Savannah, GA; Parris Island, SC; and Beauford, SC, 1979 February 12-13 (Box 116–117)
  - 29: Christopher Phillips speaking to my brother David F. Phillips, San Francisco, CA, Friday, 1979 August 10 (Box 118)
    Another date on the cassette says April 8, 1979 -- the only way to be sure is to look in my appointment book to see when I was in SF. CP 10/22/05.
  - 30-36, 1979 November 13-1980 (Box 119, Folder 10-11)
  - 37, 1980 January 23; 1 (Box 119A)
  - 38-40, 1980 February 14-June 3 (Box 119, Folder 12-13)
  - 41: Discussion of New York trip of April 17-20 with best friend Stephen Breimer on April 21; psychic reading with Carol Dryer in Los Angeles on March 26, 1980 March-April; 2 (Box 120–121)
    Cassette A contains first part of discussion of trip (side A) and second part of psychic reading (side B); cassette B contains first part of psychic reading (side A) and second part od trip discussion (side B).
  - 42-43, 1980 May 9-28 (Box 122, Folder 14)
  - 44: Christopher Phillips speaking with J. Kelley Younger of Architectural Digest -- description of his meeting in London with Fleur Cowles in May, 1980 June 5; 1 (Box 122A)
  - 45-50, 1980 June 3-November 25 (Box 122, Folder 15-18)
  - 51-55, 1980 November 26-1981 May 4 (Box 123, Folder 19-23)
  - 56-58, 1981 May 5-July 28 (Box 124, Folder 24-26)
  - 59-61, 1981 July 29-September 30 (Box 125, Folder 27-29)
  - 62-71, 1981 November 20-1982 April (Box 126, Folder 30-34)
  - 72-84, 1982 April 17-October 7 (Box 127, Folder 35-38)
  - 85: Journey in car from New York to Roanoke, 1982 October 2; 1 (Box 127A)
  - 86-88, 1982 October 7-November 1 (Box 127, Folder 39-40)
  - 89-97, 1982 November 2-1984 February 13 (Box 128, Folder 41-45)
  - 98-100, 1983 February 11-July 5 (Box 129, Folder 46-47)
  - 101: Christopher Phillips speaking to Richard Sachs about a weekend spent with John Calmann's mother, Gerta Calmann, at Perridge House, somerset (the Calmann home)., 1983 March 9; 1 (Box 130)
  - 102, 1983 March 19-April 19 (Box 129, Folder 48)
  - 103: Draycott Place, S.W.3, 1983 March 21; 1 (Box 131)
  - 104: Draycott Place, S.W.3, 1983 March 22-28; 1 (Box 132)
  - 105-108, 1983 April 21-June 27 (Box 129, Folder 49-50)
  - 109-110, 1983 July 8-November 16 (Box 133, Folder 51-52)
  - 111: Draycott Place, describing Simchas Toarah in Golders Green, 1983 September 3 (Box 133A)
  - 112-121, 1983 September 8-1984 December 31 (Box 133, Folder 53-56)
  - 122-141, 1984 February 11-1991 February 13 (Box 134, Folder 57-63)
- Additional material, Accession 2009-M-076
  - GLF (Gay Liberation Front) e-mail, 2007 September 18-2009 April 10; 123; 1081 computer files (MSG)
- Computer files (Box 206)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.